How do you explain when things don't go as we assume?
كيف يمكننا تفسير حينما تسير الأمور كما لم نكن نتوقعها؟
Or better, how do you explain
أوبشكل أفضل، كيف يمكننا تفسير
when others are able to achieve things that seem to defy all of the assumptions?
كيف يمكن لآخرين تحقيق أمور تفوق كل التوقعات؟
For example:
على سبيل المثال:
Why is Apple so innovative?
لماذا شركة " آبل " مبتكرة دوما ؟
Year after year, after year,
سنة تلو السنة ،عاما بعد عام ،
they're more innovative than all their competition.
فهي مبتكرة أكثر من منافسيها.
And yet, they're just a computer company.
رغم أنها مجرد شركة كمبيوتر.
They're just like everyone else.
فهي كباقي الشركات.
They have the same access to the same talent,
لديها نفس الخبرات ونفس المهارات،
the same agencies,
نفس الوكالات،
the same consultants, the same media.
نفس الاستشارات، نفس وسائل الترويج.
Then why is it that they seem to have something different?
إذا لماذا تبدو وكأن لديها شيئا مختلفا عن البقية ؟
Why is it that Martin Luther King led the Civil Rights Movement?
لماذا قاد مارتن لوثر كينج حركة الحقوق المدنية ؟
He wasn't the only man who suffered in pre-civil rights America,
فهو لم يكن الوحيد الذي عانى من العنصرية
and he certainly wasn't the only great orator of the day.
ولم يكن حتما الوحيد البارع في إلقاء الخطابات في زمانه.
Why him?
لماذا هو ؟
And why is it that the Wright brothers
لماذا استطاع الأخوان " رايت "
were able to figure out controlled, powered man flight
اكتشاف كيفية الإقلاع بطائرة ذات محرك
when there were certainly other teams
في حين كانت هناك بالتأكيد فرق أخرى
who were better qualified, better funded --
كانت مؤهلة أكثر و ممولة بشكل أكبر--
and they didn't achieve powered man flight,
ولكنهم لم يستطيعوا الطيران،
and the Wright brothers beat them to it.
وكان أن هزمهما الأخوان رايت.
There's something else at play here.
هنالك شيء ما يساهم في هذا الأمر.
About three and a half years ago, I made a discovery.
منذ 3 سنوات ونصف، قمت باكتشاف أمر ما.
And this discovery profoundly changed my view on how I thought the world worked,
قد غير بصورة تامة نظرتي عن كيفية عمل هذا العالم،
and it even profoundly changed the way in which I operate in it.
وقد غير أيضا بعمق كيفية تعاملي معه.
As it turns out, there's a pattern.
فقد تبين لي أن هنالك نمط .
As it turns out, all the great inspiring leaders and organizations in the world,
تبين أن كل القادة العظام الملهمين والشركات في العالم،
whether it's Apple or Martin Luther King or the Wright brothers,
سواء كانت " آبل " أو " مارتن لوثر كينج " أو " الأخوين رايت "،
they all think, act and communicate the exact same way.
فهؤلاء جميعا يتصرفون ويتواصلون بالطريقة ذاتها تماما.
And it's the complete opposite to everyone else.
وهي بعكس ما يفعله الآخرون تماما.
All I did was codify it,
وكل ما قمت به أنا هو وضع رموز لها،
and it's probably the world's simplest idea.
وهي ربما أبسط فكرة في العالم.
I call it the golden circle.
أنا أدعوها الدائرة الذهبية .
Why? How? What?
لماذا ؟ كيف ؟ ماذا ؟
This little idea explains
تفسر هذه الفكرة البسيطة
why some organizations and some leaders are able to inspire where others aren't.
كيف أن بعض المنظمات أو القادة قادرون على الإلهام أكثر من الآخرين.
Let me define the terms really quickly.
دعوني أشرح هذا الأمر بصورة سريعة.
Every single person, every single organization on the planet
كل شخص،كل منظمة على هذا الكوكب
knows what they do, 100 percent.
يعلمون مالذي يقومون به 100%.
Some know how they do it,
والبعض منهم يعلم كيف يقومون به،
whether you call it your differentiated value proposition
سواء كان ذلك بطرق الطرح المختلفة
or your proprietary process or your USP.
أو بالملكيات العملية أو تحديد سعر الوحدات.
But very, very few people or organizations know why they do what they do.
ولكن القلة فقط ،القلة من الأشخاص والمنظمات يعلمون لمَ يفعلون.
And by "why" I don't mean "to make a profit."
وعندما أقول " لماذا " لا أعني " لكي أحقق الربح."
That's a result. It's always a result.
لأن ذلك يعد نتيجة. كان وسيبقى كذلك.
By "why," I mean: What's your purpose?
ولكن بكلمة " لماذا " أعني ما هو هدفك؟
What's your cause? What's your belief?
ما هي قضيتك ؟ ما هو إيمانك ؟
Why does your organization exist?
ولماذا منظمتك موجودة في حقل العمل ؟
Why do you get out of bed in the morning?
لماذا تنهض كل صباح من سريرك ؟
And why should anyone care?
ولماذا يجب على أحدهم الاهتمام بذلك ؟
As a result, the way we think, we act,
ونتيجة لذلك،فطريقة تفكيرنا وأفعالنا،
the way we communicate is from the outside in, it's obvious.
وطريقة تواصلنا هي من الخارج إلى الداخل، وهذا بديهي.
We go from the clearest thing to the fuzziest thing.
فنحن ننطلق من أكثر الأموروضوحا إلى أكثرها تشويشاً.
But the inspired leaders and the inspired organizations --
ولكن القادة المُلهمين والمنظمات المُلمهة --
regardless of their size, regardless of their industry --
مهما كان حجمها،ومهما كانت صناعتها--
all think, act and communicate from the inside out.
جميعها تفكر وتتصرف و تتواصل من الداخل نحو الخارج.
Let me give you an example.
دعوني أعطي مثالاً.
I use Apple because they're easy to understand and everybody gets it.
انا أستخدم آبل لأنها سهلة الاستخدام والجميع يفهم ذلك.
If Apple were like everyone else,
وإذا كانت شركة " آبل " مثل باقي الشركات،
a marketing message from them might sound like this:
وكانت رسالتها التسويقية تبدو كهذه :
"We make great computers.
نحن نصنع حواسيب عظيمة.
They're beautifully designed, simple to use and user friendly.
وهي مصممة بصورة جميلة وسهلة الاستعمال.
Want to buy one?"
هل تريد شراء واحدة منها ؟"
"Meh."
" لا "
That's how most of us communicate.
وهذه هي الطريقة التي يتواصل بها معظمنا.
That's how most marketing and sales are done,
وهكذا تتم معظم عمليات التسويق والبيع،
that's how we communicate interpersonally.
وهذه الطريقة التي نتواصل بها بين الأشخاص.
We say what we do,
فنحن نقول ما نفعل،
we say how we're different or better
ونقول كيف نرى أنفسنا مختلفين أو أفضل
and we expect some sort of a behavior,
ونتوقع تصرفات تبعاً لذلك،
Here's our new car:
وهاهو شعار سيارتنا الجديدة:
It gets great gas mileage, it has leather seats.
"لها خاصية استهلاك وبها مقاعد جلدية .
Buy our car.
اشتر سيارتنا.
But it's uninspiring.
لكن هذا غير ملهم.
Here's how Apple actually communicates.
لننظر كيف تتواصل شركة " آبل " .
"Everything we do, we believe in challenging the status quo.
" في كل ما نقوم به، نؤمن أننا نتحدى الوضع الراهن.
We believe in thinking differently.
ونؤمن بالتفكير بطريقة مختلفة.
The way we challenge the status quo
والطريقة التي نعتمدها لتحدي الوضع الراهن
is by making our products beautifully designed,
هي بصنع منتجات مصممة بجودة وجمالية عالية،
simple to use and user friendly.
سهلة الاستخدام وسهلة التعلم.
We just happen to make great computers.
وقد صادف أننا نصنع حواسيب رائعة.
Want to buy one?"
هل تريد شراء واحد منها ؟
Totally different, right?
طريقةٌ مختلفةٌ تماما أليس كذلك ؟
You're ready to buy a computer from me.
فأنت على وشك شراء حاسوب الآن مني.
I just reversed the order of the information.
وكل ما قمت به هو أنني عكست طريقة عرض المعلومات.
What it proves to us is that people don't buy what you do;
وهذا يؤكد أن الناس لا تشتري ما تقوم به،
people buy why you do it.
بل تشتري لماذا تقوم بما تقوم به.
This explains why every single person in this room
وهذا يفسر سبب أن كل شخص في هذه الغرفة
is perfectly comfortable buying a computer from Apple.
مرتاحٌ تماما لشراء حاسوب من شركة " آبل ".
But we're also perfectly comfortable
بل نحن مرتاحون جدا أيضا
buying an MP3 player from Apple, or a phone from Apple,
لشراء أجهزة " ام بي3 " من شركة " آبل " و هواتف آبل،
or a DVR from Apple.
أو مشغلات أقراص ليزرية من " آبل ".
As I said before, Apple's just a computer company.
وكما قلت فشركة " آبل " ليست سوى شركة تصنيع حواسيب.
Nothing distinguishes them structurally from any of their competitors.
ولا شيء يجعلها مختلفة بنيويا عن منافسيها.
Their competitors are equally qualified to make all of these products.
فمنافسيها مؤهلون تماما لصنع كل هذه المنتجات.
In fact, they tried.
وفي الحقيقة ،فقد حاولوا فعلا.
A few years ago, Gateway came out with flat-screen TVs.
منذ عدة سنوات اأنتجت شركة " جيت واي " شاشات تلفاز مسطحة.
They're eminently qualified to make flat-screen TVs.
وهم مؤهلون بصورة بارزة لصنع شاشات مسطحة.
They've been making flat-screen monitors for years.
لأنهم كانوا يصنعون شاشات مسطحة منذ عدة سنوات.
Nobody bought one.
ولكن لم يشترها أحد منهم.
Dell came out with MP3 players and PDAs,
أطلقت شركة "ديل أيضا أجهزة "إم بي 3" و أجهزة المساعد الرقمي الشخصي،
and they make great quality products,
وقد قدموا منتجات ذات جودة عالية جدا،
and they can make perfectly well-designed products --
وهي مصممة بصورة مميزة جدا--
and nobody bought one.
ولكن لم يشتر أحد واحدة منها قط.
In fact, talking about it now, we can't even imagine
في الحقيقية وأنا أتحدث عن هذا الآن ، لايمكننا حتى تخيل
buying an MP3 player from Dell.
أننا نشتري جهاز MP3 من ديل.
Why would you buy one from a computer company?
فلماذا تشتري واحدا إذا من شركة حواسيب؟
But we do it every day.
ولكننا نقوم بهذا كل يوم.
People don't buy what you do; they buy why you do it.
لا تشتري الناس ما تقوم به ، بل تشتري لماذا تقوم بما تقوم به.
The goal is not to do business with everybody who needs what you have.
فلا يجب أن يكون الهدف القيام بالأعمال مع كل من يحتاج ما لديك.
The goal is to do business with people who believe what you believe.
إنما الهدف أن تقوم بالأعمال مع الأشخاص الذين يؤمنون بما تؤمن به.
Here's the best part:
والجزء المفضل لدي:
None of what I'm telling you is my opinion.
أن كل ما أقوله لكم ليس رأيي.
It's all grounded in the tenets of biology.
لان كل ماقلته موجود في طبيعتنا.
Not psychology, biology.
ليس في النفسية بل في طبيعتنا.
If you look at a cross-section of the human brain,
إذا نظرنا إلى مقطع لدماغ الإنسان،
from the top down, the human brain is actually broken
من الأعلى،سوف نرى أن دماغ الإنسان مقسم
into three major components
إلى ثلاث قطاعات رئيسية
that correlate perfectly with the golden circle.
وهذا متناغم تماما مع الدائرة الذهبية.
Our newest brain, our Homo sapien brain,
ودماغنا الجديد،دماغ الهومو سابين،
our neocortex,
وقشرتنا الدماغية الحديثة،
corresponds with the "what" level.
هي التي تمثل دائرة " ماذا ".
The neocortex is responsible
فالقشرة الدماغية هي المسؤولة
for all of our rational and analytical thought and language.
عن كل أفكارنا المنطقية والتحليلية و عن اللغة.
The middle two sections make up our limbic brains,
والقسمان في المنصف يشكلان حواف الدماغ،
and our limbic brains are responsible for all of our feelings,
و هما المسؤولان عن كل عواطفنا،
like trust and loyalty.
كالثقة والولاء.
It's also responsible for all human behavior,
وهما أيضا مسؤولان عن تصرفات الإنسان كلها،
all decision-making,
وكل عمليات اتخاذ القرار،
and it has no capacity for language.
ولكن لا قدرة لها على صنع اللغة.
In other words, when we communicate from the outside in,
بمعنى آخر،عندما نتواصل من الخارج إلى الداخل،
yes, people can understand vast amounts of complicated information
نعم، يستطيع الناس فهم كميات كبيرة من المعلومات المعقدة
like features and benefits and facts and figures.
مثل الميزات والحقائق والأرقام.
It just doesn't drive behavior.
هذا لا يثير سلوكا.
When we can communicate from the inside out,
ولكن عندما نتواصل من الداخل إلى الخارج،
we're talking directly to the part of the brain
فإننا نتحدث مباشرة إلى قسم الدماغ
that controls behavior,
الذي يتحكم بالتصرفات،
and then we allow people to rationalize it with the tangible things we say and do.
حينها سنسمح للناس بعقلنتها بالأشياء المحسوسة التي نقولها و نفعلها.
This is where gut decisions come from.
من هنا تصدر القرارات الفطرية.
Sometimes you can give somebody all the facts and figures,
يمكن أحيانا أن تعطي شخصا وقائع و أرقاما.
and they say, "I know what all the facts and details say,
وسيرد "أعلم ماتقوله كل تلك الحقائق و التفاصيل،
but it just doesn't feel right."
ولكنني أشعر أن هذا غير صحيح."
Why would we use that verb, it doesn't "feel" right?
لماذا استخدم هذا الفعل، "أشعر" أن هذا غير صحيح؟
Because the part of the brain that controls decision-making
ذلك لأن الجزء في الدماغ الذي يتحكم بآخذ القرارت
doesn't control language.
لا يتحكم في اللغة.
The best we can muster up is,
وأفضل ما يمكن أن نصل إليه"
"I don't know. It just doesn't feel right."
" لا أدري،أشعر أن هذا غير صحيح."
Or sometimes you say you're leading with your heart or soul.
أو أحيانا تقول أنك تتصرف تبعا لقلبك أو روحك.
I hate to break it to you, those aren't other body parts
أكره أن أقول هذا، فهذه ليست أعضاء الجسم الأخرى
controlling your behavior.
التي تتحكم بتصرفاتك.
It's all happening here in your limbic brain,
كل ذلك يحدث في حواف دماغك
the part of the brain that controls decision-making and not language.
في القسم الذي يتحكم في أخذ القرارات و ليس اللغة.
But if you don't know why you do what you do,
إذا لم تكن تعلم لماذا تقوم بما تقوم به،
and people respond to why you do what you do,
ولم يستجيب الناس للسبب الذي يقودك لما تقوم به،
then how will you ever get people
فكيف إذا تريد من الناس
to vote for you, or buy something from you,
أن تصوت لك ،أو أن تشتري منك،
or, more importantly, be loyal
أو بصورة أكثر أهمية أن تكون " مخلصة " لك
and want to be a part of what it is that you do.
أو أن ترغب في أن تكون جزء مماتقوم به.
The goal is not just to sell to people who need what you have;
ليس الهدف هو البيع للأشخاص الذين يحتاجون ما لديك،
the goal is to sell to people who believe what you believe.
إنما الهدف أن تبيع للأشخاص الذين يؤمنون بما تؤمن.
The goal is not just to hire people who need a job;
الهدف ليس أن توظف أشخاصا يحتاجون عملا،
it's to hire people who believe what you believe.
إنما توظيف أشخاص يؤمنون بما تؤمن به.
I always say that, you know,
وأنا دوما أقول هذا،
if you hire people just because they can do a job, they'll work for your money,
إن وظفت أشخاصا فقط لأنهم يستطيعون العمل فسوف يعملون من أجل مالك،
but if they believe what you believe,
ولكن إن كانوا يؤمنون بما تؤمن به،
they'll work for you with blood and sweat and tears.
فسوف يعملون معك بدمهم و عرقهم و دموعهم.
Nowhere else is there a better example than with the Wright brothers.
وليس هناك مثال أفضل من الأخوين رايت.
Most people don't know about Samuel Pierpont Langley.
معظم الناس لا تعرف صامويل بيربونت لانجلي.
And back in the early 20th century,
وقديما وفي بداية القرن العشرين،
the pursuit of powered man flight was like the dot com of the day.
كان هوس الناس بالتحليق كهوس الناس بالأنترنت اليوم.
Everybody was trying it.
كان الجميع يحاول القيام يه.
And Samuel Pierpont Langley had, what we assume,
وكان صامويل بيربونت لانجلي، كما نعتقد،
to be the recipe for success.
يملك وصفة النجاح.
Even now, you ask people,
حتى اليوم، تسأل الناس،
"Why did your product or why did your company fail?"
" لم تظن أن منتجك فشل أو شركتك فشلت ؟ "
and people always give you the same permutation
فإن معظمهم سوف يعطون نفس التبرير
of the same three things:
المتأرجح بين الأمور الثلاثة هذه :
under-capitalized, the wrong people, bad market conditions.
نقص رؤوس الأموال، توظيف الأشخاص الخطأ، ظروف السوق السيئة.
It's always the same three things, so let's explore that.
فدائما نجد هذه المبررات الثلاث، فلنكتشفها:
Samuel Pierpont Langley
تلقى صامويل بيربونت لانجلي
was given 50,000 dollars by the War Department
50 ألف دولار من قبل وزارة الحرب
to figure out this flying machine.
لكي يصمم الآلة التي تطير.
Money was no problem.
لم يكن المال مشكلة،
He held a seat at Harvard
ودرس في جامعة هارفارد
and worked at the Smithsonian and was extremely well-connected;
وكان يعمل لدى سميثسونيان وكانت لديه معارف كثيرة،
he knew all the big minds of the day.
وكان يعرف كل العقول المفكرة آنذاك.
He hired the best minds money could find
وكان قد وظف الكثير من أفضل العقول التي استطاع المال استمالتها
and the market conditions were fantastic.
وكانت ظروف السوق ممتازة.
The New York Times followed him around everywhere,
كانت النيويورك تايمز تلاحقه أينما حل،
and everyone was rooting for Langley.
وكان الجميع يستفسر عن لانجلي.
Then how come we've never heard of Samuel Pierpont Langley?
إذا فلم لم نسمع عن صامويل بيربونت لانجلي قط؟
A few hundred miles away in Dayton, Ohio,
على بعد بضع مئات من الأميال في " دايتون " أوهايو،
Orville and Wilbur Wright,
أوليفر و ويلبور رايت،
they had none of what we consider to be the recipe for success.
لم يكونا يملكان أيا مما نعتبره وصفة للنجاح.
They had no money;
لم يكونا يملكان مالا،
they paid for their dream with the proceeds from their bicycle shop.
وقد مولا حلمهما من عائدات محلهم للدراجات الهوائية،
Not a single person on the Wright brothers' team
كما أنه لم يكن أي من أعضاء فريقهما
had a college education,
يملك درجة جامعية،
not even Orville or Wilbur.
حتى أوليفر و ويلبور،
And The New York Times followed them around nowhere.
ولم تكن النيويورك تايمز تتبعتهم.
The difference was,
كان الفرق في أن
Orville and Wilbur were driven by a cause, by a purpose, by a belief.
"أوليفر و ويلبور" كانا مدفوعين بقضية، بمغزى،بإيمان.
They believed that if they could figure out this flying machine,
فقد آمنوا أنهم إن استطاعوا اكتشاف طريقة لصنع آلة للطيران،
it'll change the course of the world.
فإنهم سوف يغيرون مجرى تاريخ العالم.
Samuel Pierpont Langley was different.
كان صامويل بيربونت لانجلي مختلفا.
He wanted to be rich, and he wanted to be famous.
كان يريد الثراء والشهرة.
He was in pursuit of the result.
كان يلاحق النتيجة.
He was in pursuit of the riches.
كان يلاحق الثراء.
And lo and behold, look what happened.
وانظروا ماذا حدث جراء ذلك.
The people who believed in the Wright brothers' dream
الأشخاص الذين آمنوا بحلم الأخويت رايت
worked with them with blood and sweat and tears.
عملوا بدمهم و عرقهم و دموعهم.
The others just worked for the paycheck.
بينما كان الآخرون يعملون من أجل الرواتب.
They tell stories of how every time the Wright brothers went out,
كان يحكى أنه في كل مرة كان الأخوان رايت،
they would have to take five sets of parts,
كانا يأخذان معهما خمسا من معدات الأجزاء،
because that's how many times they would crash before supper.
لأنه هو عدد المرات التي سيتحطم فيه نموذجهم قبل العودة لتناول العشاء.
And, eventually, on December 17th, 1903,
و أخيراـفي يوم 17 ديسمبر عام 1903،
the Wright brothers took flight,
حلق الأخوان رايت،
and no one was there to even experience it.
ولم يكن هناك أحد لكي يشهد هذا الحدث.
We found out about it a few days later.
وقد علم الناس بذلك بعد بضعة أيام.
And further proof that Langley was motivated by the wrong thing:
وهذا مثال آخر كيف أن لانجلي كان مدفوعا بالشيء الخاطىء
the day the Wright brothers took flight,
وفي اليوم الذي حلق فيه الأخوان رايت،
he quit.
استقال.
He could have said,
كان بإمكانه أن يقول،
"That's an amazing discovery, guys,
" هذا اكتشاف رائع يا شباب
and I will improve upon your technology," but he didn't.
سوف أطور تكنولوجيتكم " لكنه لم يفعل ذلك.
He wasn't first, he didn't get rich, he didn't get famous, so he quit.
فلم يكن هو الأول ولم يصبح غنياً، ولم يصبح مشهورا،لذا استقال.
People don't buy what you do; they buy why you do it.
لا تشتري الناس ما تقوم به ، بل تشتري لماذا تقوم بما تقوم به.
If you talk about what you believe,
وإذا تحدثت عما تؤمن به،
you will attract those who believe what you believe.
فسوف تجذب أشخاصا يؤمنون أيضا به.
But why is it important to attract those who believe what you believe?
ولكن لم من المهم أن تجذب أشخاصا يؤمنون بما تؤمن به؟
Something called the law of diffusion of innovation,
إنه ما يسمى بقانون نشر الابتكار،
if you don't know the law, you know the terminology.
وان لم تكن تعرف هذا القانون، فإنك تعرف ما تعنيه مصطلحاته.
The first 2.5% of our population are our innovators.
2.5 % الأولى من سكان العالم هم مبتكرون.
The next 13.5% of our population are our early adopters.
و13.5 % التالية هم السباقون لتبني الابتكارات.
The next 34% are your early majority,
و 34% منهم هم أغلبية متقدمة،
your late majority and your laggards.
ثم الأغلبية الخاملة ثم المتراجعة.
The only reason these people buy touch-tone phones
والسبب الوحيد الذي يجعل هؤلاء الناس يشترون هواتف ذات لوحة ملموسة
is because you can't buy rotary phones anymore.
هو أنهم لا يستطيعون شراء هواتف تقليدية بعد اليوم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We all sit at various places at various times on this scale,
كلنا موجودون في أماكن و أزمنة مختلفة على هذا الأساس،
but what the law of diffusion of innovation tells us
ولكن مايخبرنا به قانون نشر الابتكار
is that if you want mass-market success or mass-market acceptance of an idea,
أنه إن أردت تحقيق نجاح كاسح في السوق، أو تقبل كاسح لفكرتك في السوق،
you cannot have it until you achieve this tipping point
فلا يمكنك ذلك حتى تصل إلى النقطة
between 15 and 18 percent market penetration,
تسيطر بها على 15%-18% من السوق،
and then the system tips.
ومن ثم سيتجاوب معك النظام.
I love asking businesses, "What's your conversion on new business?"
أحب أن أسأل أصحاب الأعمال، كم هي نسبة تحولكم إلى أعمال جديدة؟"
They love to tell you, "It's about 10 percent," proudly.
يحبون أن يردون،"حوالي 10 في المئة،" بكل فخر.
Well, you can trip over 10% of the customers.
ولكن 10% من حصة السوق هو رقم يسهل تجاوزه.
We all have about 10% who just "get it."
فجميعنا لدينا حوالي 10 %، ممن "يفهمون".
That's how we describe them, right?
هكذا نصفهم،صحيح؟
So it's this here, this little gap that you have to close,
إنه هذه هنا،الفراغ الصغير هنا الذي عليك أن تسده،
as Jeffrey Moore calls it, "Crossing the Chasm" --
كما يقول جيفري مور،" ردم الهوة"--
because, you see, the early majority will not try something
لأنه كما ترى الأغلبية المتقدمة لن تجرب شيئا جديداً
until someone else has tried it first.
إلا أن يقوم غيرهم بتجربته أولا.
And these guys, the innovators and the early adopters,
وهؤلاء المبتكرون و متبنو الابتكارات ،
they're comfortable making those gut decisions.
هم اللذين يتصرفون بحدسهم بكل سلاسة.
They're more comfortable making those intuitive decisions
فهم أكثرارتياحا للقيام بتلك القرارات الحدسية
that are driven by what they believe about the world
والتي تتحكم بها قناعاتهم عن العالم
and not just what product is available.
وليس حسب المنتوج المتوفر.
These are the people who stood in line for six hours
هؤلاء هم الناس الذين وقفوا في صف لست ساعات
to buy an iPhone when they first came out,
فقط لشراء هاتف " آي فون " عندما طرح لأول مرة،
when you could have bought one off the shelf the next week.
في حين أنهم كانوا يستطيعون اقتناء واحد من الرف في الأسبوع الموالي.
These are the people who spent 40,000 dollars
هؤلاء هم الأشخاص الذين أنفقوا 40،000 دولار
on flat-screen TVs when they first came out,
لشراء شاشات التلفاز المسطحة فور طرحها،
even though the technology was substandard.
حتى لو كانت هذه التكنولوجيا غير ضرورية.
And, by the way, they didn't do it because the technology was so great;
وبالمناسبة،لم يشتروها لأن التكنولوجيا كانت رائعة،
they did it for themselves.
لكنه قاموا بذلك من أجلهم.
It's because they wanted to be first.
لأنهم أرادوا أن يكونوا هم الأوائل.
People don't buy what you do; they buy why you do it
الناس لا تشتري ما تقوم به، بل تشتري لماذا تقوم بما تقوم به
and what you do simply proves what you believe.
وماتقوم به يؤكد ببساطة ماتؤمن به.
In fact, people will do the things that prove what they believe.
وفي الواقع،يقوم الناس بأشياء تؤكد مايؤمنون به.
The reason that person bought the iPhone in the first six hours,
فالسبب الذي يجعل ذلك الشخص يشتري آي فون في الساعات الست الأولى من طرحه،
stood in line for six hours,
ويقف في صف لمدة ست ساعات،
was because of what they believed about the world,
هو ما كانوا يؤمنون به حيال العالم،
and how they wanted everybody to see them:
وكيف كانوا يريدون أن يراهم الجميع:
they were first.
أنهم هم الأوائل.
People don't buy what you do; they buy why you do it.
لا تشتري الناس ما تقوم به، بل يشترون لم اذا تقوم به.
So let me give you a famous example,
دعوني أعطيكم مثالاً شهيراً،
a famous failure and a famous success of the law of diffusion of innovation.
مثالاً شهيراً عن نجاح وفشل قانون نشر الابتكار.
First, the famous failure.
أولا مثال الفشل الشهير.
It's a commercial example.
إنه مثال تجاري.
As we said before, the recipe for success
كما قلنا منذ قليل،وصفة النجاح
is money and the right people and the right market conditions.
المال، الأشخاص المناسبون و ظروف السوق المناسبة.
You should have success then.
وبهذا يتوجب عليك أن تحقق النجاح.
Look at TiVo.
انظروا إلى شركة تيفو.
From the time TiVo came out about eight or nine years ago
منذ اليوم الأول لانطلاق تيفو منذ حوالي 8 أو 9 سنوات
to this current day,
وحتى يومنا هذا،
they are the single highest-quality product on the market,
هي الشركة الوحيدة التي تبيع المنتوج الأكثر جودة في السوق،
hands down, there is no dispute.
ولا أخد يختلف مع هذا الرأي.
They were extremely well-funded.
فهم مُمَولون بصورة ممتازة.
Market conditions were fantastic.
وظروف السوق رائعة بالنسبة لهم.
I mean, we use TiVo as verb.
أعني أننا نستخدم كلمة " تيفو " كفعل.
I TiVo stuff on my piece-of-junk Time Warner DVR all the time.
أقوم ب " تيفو " على محرك الأقراص الليزرية من شكرة تايم وارنر دائما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But TiVo's a commercial failure.
ولكن تيفو تجربة تجارية فاشلة.
They've never made money.
لم يجنوا أموالا مطلقا.
And when they went IPO,
وحين طرحوا الشركة للاكتتاب العام،
their stock was at about 30 or 40 dollars
كانت قيمة أسهمهم تتراوح بين 30-40 دولارا
and then plummeted, and it's never traded above 10.
ومن ثم انخفضت، ولم ترتفع قط فوق 10 دولارات.
In fact, I don't think it's even traded above six,
في الحقيقة لا أعتقد أنها تجاوزت ال 6 دولارات،
except for a couple of little spikes.
إلا في حالات ارتفاع قليلة.
Because you see, when TiVo launched their product,
لأنه كما ترون عندما أطلقت " تيفو " منتجها،
they told us all what they had.
أخبرونا بكل ما يملكون.
They said, "We have a product that pauses live TV,
فقالوا " نحن نملك منتجا يمكنه إيقاف البث المباشر مؤقتاً،
skips commercials, rewinds live TV and memorizes your viewing habits
وتجاوز الإعلانات،وإعادة البث المباشر، وحفظ عادات المستخدم
without you even asking."
دون أدنى تدخل منه ."
And the cynical majority said,
وردت الأغلبية الساخرة،
"We don't believe you.
نحن لا نصدقكم.
We don't need it. We don't like it.
ونحن لا نحتاج لمنتجكم ولم يعجبنا.
You're scaring us."
أنتم تخيفوننا."
What if they had said,
ماذا لو قالوا التالي:
"If you're the kind of person who likes to have total control
إذا كنتم من الناس الذين يحبون أن تكون لكم السيطرة الكاملة
over every aspect of your life,
على كل جانب من جوانب حياتكم،
boy, do we have a product for you.
ياصاح، لدينا المنتج المناسب لك.
It pauses live TV, skips commercials,
فهويوقف المباشرمؤقتاً، ويتجاوز الإعلانات،
memorizes your viewing habits, etc., etc."
ويحفظ عادات المشاهدة،إلخ،إلخ."
People don't buy what you do; they buy why you do it,
لاتشتري ما تقوم به، بل تشتري لماذا تقوم بما تقوم به،
and what you do simply serves as the proof of what you believe.
لأن ماتقوم به يدل ببساطة عما تؤمن به.
Now let me give you a successful example of the law of diffusion of innovation.
دعوني الآن أعطيكم مثالا عن نجاح قانون نشر الابتكار.
In the summer of 1963,
في صيف 1963،
250,000 people showed up on the mall in Washington
اجتمع 250،000 شخصا في المجمع التجاري في واشنطن
to hear Dr. King speak.
للاستماع لخطاب الدكتور كنج.
They sent out no invitations,
لم يرسلوا أي دعوات،
and there was no website to check the date.
ولم يكن هناك موقع للتحقق من التاريخ.
How do you do that?
فكيف قام بهذا ؟
Well, Dr. King wasn't the only man in America
حسنا لم يكن د.كنج الرجل الوحيد في أمريكا
who was a great orator.
الذي يملك قدرات خطابية رائعة.
He wasn't the only man in America who suffered
ولم يكن الرجل الوحيد في أمريكا الذي عانى
in a pre-civil rights America.
من التميز العنصري في أمريكا.
In fact, some of his ideas were bad.
في الحقيقة،كانت بعض من أفكاره سيئة.
But he had a gift.
ولكنه كان يملك موهبة.
He didn't go around telling people what needed to change in America.
فهو لم يجل ليخبر الناس عما عليه أن يتغير لفي أمريكا.
He went around and told people what he believed.
بل جال عليهم وأخبرهم بما كان يؤمن به.
"I believe, I believe, I believe," he told people.
"أنا أؤمن، أنا أؤمن ، أنا أؤمن، " هذا ما قاله للناس.
And people who believed what he believed
فكان من الناس الذين آمنوا بما آمن به
took his cause, and they made it their own, and they told people.
أن تبنوا قضيته،وأخبروا الناس بها.
And some of those people created structures
فقام بعضهم بخلق مؤسسات
to get the word out to even more people.
لكي يوصلوا كلمته لجموع أكبر.
And lo and behold, 250,000 people showed up
وتبعاً لهذا، حضر 250،000 شخص
on the right day at the right time to hear him speak.
في اليوم المناسب، والوقت المناسب لكي يستمعوا إلى خطابه.
How many of them showed up for him?
كم عدد الأشخاص الذي حضروا من أجله؟
Zero.
لا أحد.
They showed up for themselves.
الجميع جاءوا من أجل أنفسهم.
It's what they believed about America
إن ماآمنوا به بشأن أمريكا
that got them to travel in a bus for eight hours
هو ما جعلهم يسافرون في الحافلات ل8 ساعات
to stand in the sun in Washington in the middle of August.
ليقفوا تحت الشمس في شهر أغسطس في واشنطن.
It's what they believed, and it wasn't about black versus white:
إنه ما آمنوا به، لم يكن عدد البيض مقابل السود:
25% of the audience was white.
وقد كان 25% من الحضور من البيض.
Dr. King believed that there are two types of laws in this world:
آمن د.كينج، أن هناك نوعين من القوانين في العالم:
those that are made by a higher authority and those that are made by men.
تلك التي وضعتها القوى العليا، والأخرى التي وضعها الناس.
And not until all the laws that are made by men
وليس حتى تصبح جميع القوانين الموضوعة من قبل البشر
are consistent with the laws made by the higher authority
متناغمة مع تلك الموضوعة من قبل الله
will we live in a just world.
حينها سنعيش في عالم عادل.
It just so happened that the Civil Rights Movement
وقد صادف أن تكون حركة الحقوق المدينة
was the perfect thing to help him bring his cause to life.
الأمر الأفضل الذي ساعده على في جلب قضيته إلى الواجهة .
We followed, not for him, but for ourselves.
وقد اتبعناه لا لشخصه ،بل لأنفسنا.
By the way, he gave the "I have a dream" speech,
وبالمناسبة،فقد ألقى خطاب " لدي حلم،"
not the "I have a plan" speech.
ولم يلقي خطاب " لدي خطة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Listen to politicians now, with their comprehensive 12-point plans.
استمعوا للسياسيين اليوم، وخططهم التي تشمل 12 بندا.
They're not inspiring anybody.
ليست ملهمة لأي أحد.
Because there are leaders and there are those who lead.
ولأن هناك قادة،وهناك من يقود الناس.
Leaders hold a position of power or authority,
قادة يشغلون منصب سلطة أوقوة،
but those who lead inspire us.
لكن من يقودون يلهموننا.
Whether they're individuals or organizations,
سواء كان فرداً أو منظمة،
we follow those who lead, not because we have to,
فنحن نتبع من يقودون، ليس أنه يتوجب علينا ذلك،
but because we want to.
بل لأننا نريد ذلك.
We follow those who lead, not for them, but for ourselves.
نتبع من يقودون،ليس من أجلهم، بل لأجل أنفسنا.
And it's those who start with "why"
وهؤلاء الذين يبدأون ب " لماذا "
that have the ability to inspire those around them
هم الذين لديهم المقدرة على إلهام الناس من حولهم
or find others who inspire them.
أو إيجاد آخرين يلهمونهم.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)